Preliminary Guide to the Phillip Rhodes papers, 1958-2004
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Phillip Rhodes papers 1958-2004
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Rhodes, Phillip
71.5 Linear Feet 7186 Items
North Carolina born and raised composer, Duke alumn, and composer-in-residence and professor at Carleton College.
Collection comprises primarily scores, instrumental parts, notes, and recordings that follow the development of each of Rhodes' compositions. There are published and unpublished works for vocal and instrumental preformance, as well as correspondence, programs, newspaper clippings, and other publicity and related items. Included are also 34 CDs, 2 audiocassettes, and 1 videocassette, as well as photographs. The 2007 Addition (07-061)(1600 items, 2.5 lin. ft.; dated 1960s-2004) primarily contains professional files and correspondence related to Rhodes' career. Files include music festivals; premieres and other performances of Rhodes' works; correspondence with performers, other composers, and record companies; and some clippings and other memorabilia.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Phillip Rhodes papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2006, 2007.
Biographical Note
Composer-in-Residence and Andrew W. Mellon Professor of the Humanities at Carleton College where he joined the faculty in 1974. His principal teachers have been William Klenz, Iain Hamilton, Donald Martino, and Mel Powell. Born in Forest City, North Carolina in 1940, he received degrees from Duke University and the Yale University School of Music. Rhodes has been the recipient of numerous commissions and composition awards, including grants from the National Endowment for the Arts, the National Endowment for the Humanities, the Rockefeller Fund for Music, a citation and award from the American Academy of Arts and Letters, a Guggenheim Fellowship, two Tanglewood Orchestra Prizes, two McKnight Foundation Fellowships, two Fromm Foundation Commissions (Harvard), and a Bush Foundation Fellowship for Artists. Rhodes' compositions are published by C. F. Peters, E.M.I., Theodore Presser, J Ballerbach, and Schott, and recorded on labels including CRI, Centaur Records, First Edition (Louisville), Innova, New World Records, and Vienna Modern Masters.
Collection Overview
Collection comprises primarily scores, instrumental parts, notes, and recordings that follow the development of each of Rhodes' compositions. There are published and unpublished works for vocal and instrumental preformance, as well as correspondence, programs, newspaper clippings, and other publicity and related items. Included are also 34 CDs, 2 audiocassettes, and 1 videocassette, as well as photographs.
The 2007 addition (07-061)(1600 items, 2.5 lin. ft.; dated 1960s-2004) primarily contains professional files and correspondence related to Rhodes' career. Files include music festivals; premieres and other performances of Rhodes' works; correspondence with performers, other composers, and record companies; and clippings and other memorabilia.
Addition (2008-0185)(50 items, .5 lin. ft.; dated 1959-2008) contains 41 CDs featuring audio recordings of performances of Rhodes compositions and arrangements, an original score for Sweet River Waltz, and notes and drafts related to compositions from 2007.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Rhodes, Phillip
Carleton College. (Northfield, Minn.)
Music -- Manuscripts
Composers -- United States
Composers -- United States -- Correspondence
Compact discs
Audiocassettes
Photographs
Contents of Collection
- Accession, 2006 (2006-0014), 48 Boxes
  Accession comprises primarily scores, instrumental parts, notes, and recordings that follow the development of each of Rhodes' compositions. There are published and unpublished works for vocal and instrumental preformance, as well as correspondence, programs, newspaper clippings, and other publicity and related items. Included are also 34 CDs, 2 audiocassettes, and 1 videocassette, as well as photographs.
  - Madrigal, 1967 (Box 1)
    for orchestra and SATB chorus
    Commissioned by the ELgin (ILL) Public Schools. Published (rental) by Theodore Presser, Bryn Mawr.
  - Autumn Setting, 1969
    for soprano and string quartet
    Commissioned by the Fromm Music Foundation (Harvard University) and the Berkshire Music Center (Tanglewood Festival). Published by C.F. Peters, New York.
  - Recordings, (Compact discs) (Box 2)
    - Three French songs
    - Three scenes for voice and piano
    - Three pieces for solo cello
    - Duo for violin and cello
    - Autumn setting for soprano and string quartet
    - Remembrance
    - Three pieces for band
    - Cosmic fantasies
    - March parody
    - Devil's advocate
    - Wind songs
    - Dancing songs
    - The lament of Michael
    - Divertimento for small orchestra
    - Witticisms and lamentations from the graveyard
    - Prayers from the Psalms
    - Five songs on children's poems
    - String trio
    - Museum pieces
    - Concerto for bluegrass band and orchestra
    - Quartet for flute, violin, cello and harp
    - Cantata: On the morning of Christ's nativity
    - Mountain songs
    - Reflections: Eight fantasies for piano
    - Partita for solo viola
    - Visions of remembrance
    - Ad honorem Stravinsky
    - The face I carry with me
    - Recording of two published excerpts from Nets to catch the wind
    - Wedding song: a blessing
    - Reels and Reveries
    - Excerpt publication from Nets to Catch the Wind
    - Excerpt publication from the Christmas Cantata, On the morning of Christ's nativity
    - Fiddletunes
    - Chorale and organ meditation
    - Chorale fantasy for organ (O sacred head, now wounded)
    - A love song (string quartet)
    - Operas and oratorios
      - From paradise lost
      - The gentle boy
      - The magic pipe
  - Cassette tape recording of Martinomezzo
  - Duo for violin and cello, 1967 (Box 3)
    Commissioned by the violinst, Paul Zukofsky. Published by C.F. Peters, New York.
  - Programs
  - Correspondence
  - Notebooks
  - Class materials
  - Programs and program notes from concerts Rhodes sponsored and on which his music was played, 1967 (Box 4)
  - Programs for concert band works
  - Dancing songs, 1984-1985
    For children's voices and Orff instrumentarium.
    Commissioned by the American Orff-Schulwerk Association. Published by Schott (London).
  - Programs and program notes
  - Scores (Box 5)
  - Scores (Box 6)
  - Correspondence
  - Remembrance, 1967 (Box 7)
    For concert band.
    Published by Theodore Presser (rental).
  - Cosmic fantasies, 1983 (Box 8)
    Originally titled Adventure fantasies for young players.
    Published by J. Ballerbach.
  - Three Kentucky songs, 1973
    For treble choir and piano.
    Commissioned by the Kentucky Music Educators Association. Published by the Kentucky Music Educators Association.
  - Wind songs, 1979
    For children's choir and Orff instrumentarium.
    Commissioned for the Northfield Public Schools with funding from the Minnesota State Arts Board. Published by Schott (London).
  - Correspondence
  - Scores (Box 9)
  - Programs
  - The Devils' advocate, 1972 (Box 10)
    Commmissioned by Paul R. Bryan for Duke University Symphony Band.
  - Cosmic fantasies for concert band, 1983
  - March parody (with variations), 2001-2002
  - Correspondence
  - The Devils' advocate, 1972 (Box 11)
  - Remembrance, 1967
  - Three pieces for band, 1967
    Commmissioned by the National Band Association.
  - Correspondence
  - Shakespeare in song, 1999-2000 (Box 12)
    For high voice, clarinet and piano.
    Texts from the Shakespeare plays. Commissioned by tenor, James McDonald, Professor of Voice, Indiana University.
  - Cluck ol' hen from Three Appalachian settings, 2005
    Published by earthsongs music, Corvallis, Oregon.
  - Two Appalachian settings, 1995-2002
    For string quartet.
  - Correspondence (Box 13)
  - Fanfare and reflections on the Carleton College Alma Mater, 2002
    For brass choir.
    An occasional piece commissioned by Carleton College to mark the retirement of Stephen R. Lewis, Jr. as President of the College (1987-2002).
  - Meditations upon Lactantius' "De ave phoenice", 2002-2003
    For bassoon and harp.
    Commissioned by Jackson Bryce through the David Bryn-Jones Endowed Professorship.
  - Three Gershwin settings, 2000-2004
    Ffor violin and piano.
    Someone to watch over me commissioned by Anna Jean Rhodes and Alan J. Lipsky to celebrate their marriage. Summertime fantasy and I got (fascinating) rhythm commissioned by Kathryn Ananda-Owens and Hector Luis Valdivia for concert use.
  - Bluegrass and country dances arrangements
    Beginning in 1973 (and continuing for a number of years), the Berea College Country Dancers and the McLain Family Bluegrass Band were engaged by the CIncinnati Symphony Orchestra to tour with the orchestra's summer programs. It was a good, old-fashioned event: the CSO softball team would play the local team in the afternoon, followed by a picnic supper, and ending with a concert (usually outdoors) in the evening. Enclosed is the program book from 1974.
    Since I was at the time Composer-in-Residence for the Kentucky State Arts Commission, I was hired by the CSO to do the orchestral arrangements for both groups.
    My work with the MCLain Family Band eventually led to the Concerto for Bluegrass Band and Orchestra (a.k.a. Bluegrass Festival Suite) which was commissioned jointly by the National Endowment for the Arts and the Kentucky Arts Commission to celebrate the national bicentennial. This work has subsequently been performed more than 200 times from Alaska to Florida. (PR)
    - Orchestral arrangements for the Berea College Country Dancers
      - English country dance suite, 1974
        - 1. The parson's farewell
        - 2. The hare's maggott
      - Leapfrog
      - Appalachian square dance
    - Orchestral arrangements for the McLain Family Band (Box 14)
      - Live it up, honey, 1974
      - High hopes, 1974
      - Movin' on to higher ground, 1974
      - One step at a time, 1974
      - Silver creek, 1974
      - You sing for me, 1978
      - Come out tonight, 1978
      - Back up and push, 1978
      - On the road, 1978
      - Bound for gloryland, 1980
  - Scores (Box 15)
  - Programs
  - Scores (Box 16)
  - Programs
  - Notes
  - Scores (Box 17)
  - Scores (Box 18)
  - Three scenes for voice and piano (Mezzo sop.), 1964-1965 (Box 19)
  - Kyrie, 1966-1967
    SSA, a cappella
    Published score, C. F. Peters, New York.
  - Ensemble Etudes, 1967
    For string quartet and woodwind quintet.
  - Three pieces for solo cello 1965-1966
    This piece was the first publication of Rhodes' music by C.F. Peters, New York.
  - Ensemble Etudes, 1967 (Box 20)
  - Three pieces for solo cello 1965-1966
  - Three Bs, 1971 (Box 20)
    For orchestra.
    For the Louisville-Jefferson County Youth Orchestra.
  - Suite no. 2 for five winds, 1962 (Box 21)
  - Recollections of a summer past, 1962
    For high voice and piano.
    Poetry by Millard C. Dunn, Duke 1962.
  - Four movements for chamber orchestra, 1962
    Winner of Tanglewood Orchestra Prize, 1962
  - Original score of String trio, 1964-1965
    For violin, viola, and cello.
    BMI Student Composers Award, 1965. Later revised and published in 1973.
  - Notebook
  - Three French songs, 1961 (Box 22)
    For SATB, a cappella.
    Poetry by Millard C. Dunn, Duke 1962. Published in 2000 by J. Ballerbach, San Antonio
  - Manuscript scores of three unfinished large pieces, 1962 and 1967 and an orchestration class assignment from Duke, 1962
  - An arrangement of Grenada for a high school friend, Patricia Blanton, as her talent piece in the Miss North Carolina Pagent, 1963
  - Five songs on children's poems, 1972
    For soprano and piano.
    For the Kentucky Arts Commission.
  - Partita, 1978
    For solo viola.
    Commissioned by the violist, Ann Woodward. Published by C.F. Peters, New York.
  - Correspondence
  - March, 1961 (Box 23)
    For woodwind quintet.
  - Notes on an unfinished brass trio, Tanglewood, 1965
  - Unidentified notebook, Work notes on early pieces, 1962-1966
  - Score of Fugue in C minor; awarded the Frances E. Osborne Kellogg Fugue Prize (Yale School of Music, 1965)
  - String Trio, 1965 (rev. 1973)
    For violin, viola and cello.
    Published by C.F. Peters, New York.
  - Notebooks
  - Prayers from the psalms, 1972 (Box 24)
    For soprano, SATB chorus and organ.
    For the Bradley Hills Presbyterian Church of Bethesda, MD.
  - Museum pieces, 1973
    For clarinet and string quartet.
    Commissioned by the J.B. Speed Art Museum of Louisville. Published by C.F. Peters, New York.
  - Divermento for small orchestra, 1971 (Box 25)
    Commissioned by the Kentucky Chamber Orchestra. Published by C.F. Peters, New York.
  - Witticisms and lamentations from the graveyard,1972
    For the Berea College Choir. Published by C.F. Peters, New York.
  - Ceremonial fanfare and chorale, 1977
    For double brass choir.
    To celebrate the inauguration of Robert Edwards as President of Carleton College.
  - Anniversary Waltz for Pat and Peter, 1970 (not finished) (Box 26)
  - "Benediction" setting, 1973
    For the Berea College Choir.
  - Cantata: "On the morning of Christ's nativity", 1976
    For soprano and tenor soli, SATB chorus, flute, oboe, trumpet, bassoon and harp.
    Text from John Milton's ode of the same name. Published by C.F. Peters, New York.
  - Newspaper clippings
  - Programs (Box 27)
  - Newspaper clippings
  - Correspondence (Box 28-35)
  - About faces ballet, 1970 (Box 36)
    For chamber orchestra.
    Commissioned by the Kentucky Dance Theater. Published (rental) by C.F. Peters, New York.
  - Concerto for bluegrass band and orchestra (a.k.a. Bluegrass Festival Suite), 1974 (Box 37)
    Commissioned by the NEA and the Kentucky Arts Commission. Published by EMI, New York (G. Schirmer, agent).
  - Mountain songs (a ballad cycle), 1976 (Box 38)
    Commissioned by the National Association of Teachers of Singing. Published by C.F. Peters, New York.
  - Relections: Eight fantasies for piano, 1976-1977
    Commissioned by the National Endowment for the Arts. Published by C.F. Peters, New York.
  - The lament of Michal, 1970 (Box 39)
    for soprano and orchestra
    Commissioned by the Louisville Orchestra. Published (rental) by C.F. Peters, New York.
  - Visions of remembrance, 1978-1979
    for soprano, mezzo soprano and 12 instruments
    Commissioned by Carleton College for the Contemporary Chamber Ensemble. Published by C.F. Peters, New York (rental).
  - Visions of remembrance, 1978-1979 (Box 40)
  - Quartet, 1975 (Box 41)
    for flute, violin, cello and harp
    Commissioned by the Fromm Music Foundation (Harvard University) for Seculum Musicae of New York. Published by C.F. Peters, New York.
  - Newts to catch the wind, 1986 (Box 42)
    SATB with percussion
    Commissioned by three professional choruses through the National Endowment for the Arts. Excerpt publicaton by C.F. Peters, New York
  - Ad honorem Stravinsky, 1981 (Box 43)
    for SATB, a cappella
    Published by C.F. Peters, New York
  - In praise of wisdom, 1982
    SATB and brass choir
    Commissioned by West Virginia Wesleyan College for their 100th Anniversary.
  - The face I carry with me on poems of Emily Dickinson, 1982
    Soprano, flute, viola, cello and piano
    Commissioned by the Chicago Ensemble.
  - Inaugural processional, 1987 (Box 44)
    Commissioned by Carleton College for the inauguration of Stephen R. Lewis, Jr. as its ninth president.
  - Concert programs
  - Official performance notices from publishers
  - Martinomezzo (A birthday card), 1991
    for clarinet with extension
    For Martino Festschrift publication in Perspectives of new music.
  - Reels and reveries (Variations for orchestra), 1991 (rev. 1992)
    Commissioned by the Owensboro Symphony Orchestra to dedicate a new arts center. Published (rental) by C.F. Peters, New York.
  - Reels and reveries (Variations for orchestra), 1991 (rev. 1992) (Box 45)
  - Mary's lullaby, 1993
    A Christmas piece for soprano, violin, and organ.
  - Chorale and organ meditation, 1994
    SSAA, organ
    Commissioned by the First United Church of Christ, Northfield for the dedication of a new organ.
  - Fiddletunes, 1994-1995
    for solo violin and synthesized strings
  - Wedding song: a blessing, 1990 (Box 46)
    Soprano, violin, and organ
  - Chorale fantasy, 1995
    for organ
    On O sacred heart, now wounded
  - A love song, 1998
    for string quartet
    Originally written for our son's wedding (a revised version later used in Two Appalachian settings for string quartet.)
  - Excerpt publication from the Christmas cantata, On the morning of Christ's nativity, 1998
  - Excerpt publication from Nets to catch the wind, 1998
    This work was originally commissioned throught the National Endowment for the Arts by a consortium of three professional choruses: The Paul Hill Chorale (Washington, DC), the Gregg Smith Singers (New York), and the Oregon Repertory Singers (Portland).
  - Operas and oratorios
    - Opera-Oratorio: From paradise lost, 1972 (Box 3, 4, 6, 7, 8, 17, 18, 20)
      for narrator, soprano, tenor, baritone soloists, SATB chorus, and large orchestra
      Text from John Milton's epic poem.
      Commissioned by the Courier-Journal and Louisville Times Foundation for the Louisville Orchestra. Recorded on First Edition Records in 1972 as a 2-Record Set, LS-723, 723. Published (rental) by C.F. Peters, New York.
    - The gentle boy, Opera in one act,1980 (rev. 1987) (Box 4-6, 14-17)
      for soprano, mezzo, tenor, baritone soloists, SATB chorus, and chamber orchestra
      Based on the Hawthorne short story of the same name.
      Winner of the National Opera Association's New Opera Competition in 1986.
    - The magic pipe, Opera in one act,1990-1991 (Box 44, 46-48)
      for soprano, mezzo, tenor, baritone soloists, SATB chorus, and two pianos
      Based on the Hawthorne short story, Feathertop.
      Commissioned by Carleton College to celebrate its 125th anniversary. One of three finalists in the National Opera Association's New Opera Competition, 1994.
    - Videocassette of a performance of The magic pipe (Box 47)
    - Proposed grand opera project - unfinished - called Odysseus, 1974-1977 (Box 46)
      Enclosed are working notes, draft of manuscript full score (composed excerpts intended to show opera people.
      Libretto (by Dr. Benjamin Bradford.
- Accession, 2007 (2007-0061), 6 Boxes
  Addition (dated 1960s-2004) primarily contains professional files and correspondence related to Rhodes’ career. Files include music festivals; premieres and other performances of Rhodes’ works; correspondence with performers, other composers, and record companies; and some clippings and other memorabilia.
  - Festival and conference files (Box 48)
  - Festival and conference files (Box 49)
  - Professional files (Box 50)
    - Recording company files
    - Performance ensembles files
    - Grant applications
  - Festival and conference files (Box 51)
  - Festival and conference files
  - Professional files
  - Concert programs and memorabilia, 1960s
  - Concert programs and memorabilia, 1970s
  - Concert programs and memorabilia, 1980s
  - Concert programs and memorabilia, 1990s
  - Concert programs and memorabilia, 2000s
  - Professional correspondence (Box 52)
  - Oversize materials (Box 53)
    - Newspaper clippings and articles, 1962-1968
    - Items from residency in Louisville, 1969-1974
      - Programs
      - Newspaper clippings and articles
- Accession (2008-0185), 1959-2007, 1 Box
  Addition (2008-0185)(50 items, .5 lin. ft.; dated 1959-2008) contains 41 CDs featuring audio recordings of performances of Rhodes compositions and arrangements, an original score for Sweet River Waltz, and notes and drafts related to compositions from 2007.
  - Works written from 1959-1969 (10 CDs) (Box 54)
  - Works written from 1970-1979 (14 CDs)
  - Works written from 1980-1989 (4 CDs)
  - Works written from 1990-1999 (1 CD)
  - Works written from 2000- (2 CDs)
  - Operas and Oratorios (5 CDs)
  - Bluegrass Orchestral Arrangements (1 CD)
  - Works for Concert Band and Large Wind Ensemble (4 CDs)
  - Score: Sweet River Waltz
  - New Compositions, 2007